<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Emma Chisit</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2018-12-29T15:45:05+02:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name></name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[More polls and more movement towards the ALP]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/more-movement/" />
  <id>/more-movement</id>
  <published>2016-04-05T00:00:00+03:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-05T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The Emma Chisit model &lt;a href=&quot;http://auselections.com/current-forecast/&quot;&gt;updated&lt;/a&gt; today after a break which resulted in some changes and improvements to the model and the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been one major political announcement since the model’s last update: Prime Minister Malcolm Turnbull has signified he is willing to use a slew of industrial legislation as a double dissolution trigger which means an early election on July 2 (in less than 13 weeks) is likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as polls are concerned, it seems that Turnbull’s “honeymoon” period is drawing to a close, and we’ve seen a number of polls putting the ALP in striking distance of the Coalition, including a particularly ominous Newspoll on April 4 which put the ALP ahead for the first time since the leadership change in September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma has been a little slow to reflect these changes, but the end result is an improvement of four seats towards the ALP: the model now has them winning 61 seats, a 6-seat improvement from their 2013 result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some improvements to the model I’m currently working on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;implementing the strong transition model for runoffs as a better model of voter behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing support for marginal polls (the first of the campaign was released last week for the seat of Indi currently held by Independent Cathy McGowan)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proper support for third-parties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all these are implement in a few weeks, Emma Chisit will be fully ready. Any new poll release will trigger the model to update, including generating and uploading a new pendulum and image. I’ll keep updating this blog every few days during the campaign as well, hopefully providing some interesting commentary on the process. A reminder that the code for Emma Chisit is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/clintonboys/emma-chisit-site&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; Github repository.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/more-movement/&quot;&gt;More polls and more movement towards the ALP&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit&lt;/a&gt; on April 05, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Third forecast]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/third-forecast/" />
  <id>/third-forecast</id>
  <published>2016-02-21T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The Emma Chisit model updated today because of a Newspoll released, tying the ALP and Coalition two-party preferred vote at 50-50. Although most individual seats shifted slightly in the ALP’s favour, there was no overall change in the forecasted seat count for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emma Chisit’s heart is a poll aggregate; this allows for the chance that the Newspoll is an outlier by including older polls with decaying weights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Newspoll has a pretty bad historical record and so is included in the model with a relatively low weight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model is definitely detecting movement towards the Coalition, and another couple of polls with similar numbers could start to see the seat forecast drastically change.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/third-forecast/&quot;&gt;Third forecast&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit&lt;/a&gt; on February 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Second forecast]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/second-forecast/" />
  <id>/second-forecast</id>
  <published>2016-02-19T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The Emma Chisit model updated today in light of a few polls over the last few days. The seat forecast didn’t change, and no individual seats changed hands. I’ll note that during the intervening period between the first and second updates, Crikey’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.crikey.com.au/pollbludger/&quot;&gt;Poll Bludger&lt;/a&gt; forecast updated to precisely agree with Emma.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/second-forecast/&quot;&gt;Second forecast&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit&lt;/a&gt; on February 19, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[First forecast]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/first-forecast/" />
  <id>/first-forecast</id>
  <published>2016-02-13T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The Emma Chisit model had its official debut today: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://auselections.com/current-forecast/&quot;&gt;current forecast page&lt;/a&gt; was updated today with the first forecast model. The forecast is a little basic, as the following features of the model are still missing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;marginal polls and demographic clustering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;automatic adjustment for high-profile candidates and independents (these are currently hardcoded into the model)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;probabilistic estimates and confidence intervals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These features will all be added in the coming months as the Australian Federal election draws closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the actual prediction of the model, it is currently (as expected) very close to other poll aggregates on the web. Emma has the Coalition winning 89 seats, down one from its 90-seat haul in the 2013 election. The seat-by-seat forecast also reveals very few changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;things-to-look-out-for&quot;&gt;Things to look out for&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the coming months as the model updates (initially I will be updating it manually, but eventually it will all be automated) there are some things I will be keeping a close eye on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the model’s ability to detect the PUP vote. PUP leader Clive Palmer’s support has fallen off dramatically, and many polls do not even include PUP as an option anymore. Until I come up with a reasonable way of handling this, I’m hardcoding an advantage to Palmer in his seat of Fairfax which awards him the seat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the contest in Indi. This seat was won by an Independent in 2013 in a close contest. I’m interested to see if the model can detect changes here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;differences from other aggregates online, and from betting markets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/first-forecast/&quot;&gt;First forecast&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit&lt;/a&gt; on February 13, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Emma Chisit - setup on AWS]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/ec2-migration/" />
  <id>/ec2-migration</id>
  <published>2016-02-05T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Today I moved Emma Chisit to an EC2 server; this way I will be able to fully automate the model. My aim is to have a fully automated model set up by the time the election draws close enough for marginal polls to start being commissioned (the inclusion of marginal polls is the real point of differentiation for the Emma Chisit model).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model will perform the following workflow daily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;update its database of polls, including marginal polls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;update its poll aggregate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if there are no marginal polls, run a simple aggregate seat-by-seat swing adjustment using preference estimates and the strong transition model&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if there are, run clustering 1000 times, adjusting swings in clusters according to marginal seat polls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;automatically update the current forecast graphic and page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ec2-migration/&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit - setup on AWS&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit&lt;/a&gt; on February 05, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Emma Chisit's new home]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/emmas-new-home/" />
  <id>/emmas-new-home</id>
  <published>2015-09-02T00:00:00+03:00</published>
  <updated>2015-09-02T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri></uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Today I registered Emma Chisit’s new domain, auselections.com, and started planning the website. The idea is to start updating the model with all new poll data in the lead-up to the next Australian federal election which will probably take place some time in the next twelve months.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emmas-new-home/&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit&#39;s new home&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Emma Chisit&lt;/a&gt; on September 02, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
